בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ק"י, kuf yud, בבא
מציעא Bava Metzia 110. We pick up at the very bottom of
ק"ט עמוד ב'. kuf tet amud bet. We were at the last
line, but we're actually going to jump back a little bit to
get the context. So we're going to start where it says ההוא
גברא hahu gavra by the asterisk, it's about 12 lines from the
bottom. ההוא גברא דמשכן פרדיסא לחבריה, hahu gavra demashkin pardisa lechavrei, somebody
put as collateral, mortgaged a פרדס pardes which רש"י Rashi in this
case says means a vineyard to his friend. And this was the
case where which was משכנתא דסורא, mashkanta desura, where the creditor would
benefit from it for let's say 10 years. It's said, right? says
לעשר שנין le-eser shanin that he would go ahead and he would
take all of the produce for 10 years, and that would be
considered a payment of the loan. All right?
וקש לחמש שנין, ve-kash le-chamesh shanin, but what happened was was that
the
vines or some of the vines got old and dried out within
the within five years. And he's entitled to 10 years of produce.
So the question is: do you consider the wood of the vines
since they were dried out in their right time, this was when
they were expected, is that a type of the thing that those
vines are producing? Once they dry out they're producing their own wood
and therefore he gets those vines as well.
אביי אמר פירא הוי. Abaye amar peira havei. It's a type of
a fruit, like I just said, and the מלוה malveh gets it
for, you know, the dried wood. רבא אמר קרנא הוי. Rava amar
karna havei. No, these vines were part of the vineyard and he
doesn't get the wood of the vines, you have to treat it
like it's still part of the vineyard. So what do you do?
וילקח בו קרקע והוא אוכל פירות. Veyilakach bo karka vehu ochel peiros.
Sell sell these dried up vines for their wood and then use
that money and that money reinvest, you know, buy land or whatever,
something that he will continue to reap the פירות peiros from, but
he cannot treat this themselves as פירא. peira. Okay, so that was
the case yesterday, and we asked this question, exactly this case, מיתיבי:
meisvei: יבש האילן או נקצץ שניהם אסורין בו. yavesh kailan o niktzas
sheneihem asurin bo. If the tree dries up or it's cut down,
both the מלוה malveh and the לוה loveh can't benefit from it.
כיצד יעשו ימכרו לעצים וילקח בהן קרקע והוא אוכל פירות. Keitzad ya-asu?
Yimkru l-eitzim ve-yilakach bahen karka vehu ochel peiros. Okay, so we won't
worry about both of them not benefiting from it, but the basic
point is: exactly like רבא Rava says. You go ahead and you
convert it into קרקע karka and you treat it as קרן, keren,
as the thing itself, not as the פירות, peiros, and then the
creditor continues to get the פירות peiros from it. מאי לאו יבש
דומיא דנקצץ? Mai lav yavesh dumya de-niktzas? מה נקצץ בזמנו אף יבש
בזמנו? Ma niktzas bizmano af yavesh bizmano? So the same way when
it says it was cut down or dried up, cut down means
that it was anticipated, that was the plan. So presumably יבש yavesh
would be the same idea, and it meant it was יבש yavesh
in the time that that was expected. So you see that even
when something dries up on schedule, it's not considered to be the
fruits of the vine, it's considered to be the vine itself and
has to be converted back into some principle. So that seems to
be a strong proof for רבא. Rava. So מה נקצץ בזמנו אף
יבש בזמנו ma niktzas bizmano af yavesh bizmano וקתני וילקח בהן קרקע
והוא אוכל פירות, u-ktani yilakach bahen karka vehu ochel peiros, אלמא קרנא
הוי. alma karna havei. So you see that it's the principle. לא.
Lo. No, אביי Abaye can say back to you: נקצץ דומיא דיבש.
niktzas dumya de-yavesh. מה יבש בלא זמנו אף נקצץ בלא זמנו. Ma
yavesh belo zemano af niktzas belo zemano. No, who says? We could
be talking that both of them are when it was not the
time that it was planned, and you know, and maybe it was
cut down, you know, for some emergency reason or something. And if
it was not the time that it was planned for, then of
course אביי Abaye would say it's considered to be the קרן. keren.
This is not the normal the vine wouldn't normally dry up this
fast, so it was always considered part of the vineyard during this
period of time. So if it does dry up, you have to
convert it back into the vineyard. אביי Abaye is saying: I'm only
saying it's fruit when it dries up in the expected time, since
that's anticipated, this is then what this vine is going to produce
when it's done producing grapes. Okay, so that's what we did yesterday.
Now let's keep on going. תא שמע, Ta shema, last line of
ק"ט עמוד ב', kuf tet amud bet, come in here: נפלו לה
גפנים וזיתים זקנים. naflu lah gefanim ve-zeisim zekeinim.
So let's say a woman in her inherited
when she was married. Now this idea of eating the fruit and
who has title, that same idea is that we have by the
משכנתא דסורא mashkanta desura and the creditor and the debtor, we have
by a married woman. A married woman her property she owns, the
husband has the right for the פירות, peiros, usufruct. Okay, but she
retains the title. And this is true about property she brings into
the marriage and also property that she acquires during the marriage. So
let's say נפלו לה, naflu lah, fell to her, meaning let's say
like, you know, her father died and she inherited this, גפנים וזיתים
זקנים. gefanim ve-zeisim zekeinim. So she actually got, you know, she inherited
vineyards and olive groves, but they were all dried up. So what
do you do with it? So ימכרו לעצים וילקח בהן קרקע והוא
אוכל פירות. yimkru le-eitzim ve-yilakach bahen karka vehu ochel peiros. So sell
them, buy fruit buy land, the land is in her... title,
and he will get the and he will get the פירות. peirot.
So that's again showing you that dried up vines is considered to
be the principal, not the fruit. If it was the fruit he
would just get it right away.
So
אימא והזקינו. eima vehizkinu. No, don't read it that they're old which
means that they're naturally old, that would if that was true then
that would be a proof to רבא Rava that we always consider
them even when it's natural age, we always consider them to be
part of the principal. No, it means they got old before their
time. And that's again where אביי Abaye says I would concede to
רבא Rava it's considered the principal. But if they are just naturally
old, then they are פירות peirot and the husband could just go
ahead and pocket all that money from the wood of the vines
and of the of the olive trees. ואיבעית אימא Ve'iba'it eima if
I want you could say לאו אוקימנא לה כגון שנפלו בשדה אחרת
דכלה קרנא lav ukimna lah kegon she'naflu besadeh acheret dekala karna that
actually here's another explanation that we said that that she inherited the
vineyards and the vines and the olive trees in but she did
not own the land they were on. She only owned the vines
and the olive trees. Okay, somebody else owned the land, so that's
what she acquired. So if that's what she acquired, they're not the
fruit of the land, they are the only principal. There's no way
you could look at them as fruit. So in that case אביי
Abaye says I would concede to רבא Rava that if you only
have that, you would look at them as the principal. But if
somebody actually has the land if you both have the land and
the trees, says אביי, Abaye, you would look at them as the
fruit. Okay, that's the end of that debate. Now picking up on
a new topic. ההוא שטרא דהוה כתיב ביה שנין סתמא. Hahu shtra
dehavah ketiv beih shanin stama. There was a document that simply read,
this was again a משכנתא דסורא mashkanta desura where the owner has
the right to be eating for x number of years and then
that pays off the loan. Okay, and it was written years. The
owner can it was dated, you know, January 1st, 2020, the and
you know, not the owner, excuse me, the debtor, excuse me, the
creditor, the guy lending the money, the מלווה, malveh, the creditor, you
know, lent ראובן Reuven lent שמעון Shimon $1000, January 1st, 2020, and
this field is is a משכנתא דסורא mashkanta desura and ראובן Reuven
can eat from the fruit of it for years without a number,
and then the loan will be paid off. Okay, so how many
years? Big very important omission. דכתיב ביה שנין סתמא. Dechtiv beih shanin
stama. מלווה אמר שלש לווה אמר שתים. Malveh amar shalosh loveh amar
shtayim. The מלווה, malveh, ראובן Reuven says, it says we meant three
years and I have a right for three years of benefit. And
שמעון Shimon says, no, you only it says you know, the intention
was two years and you could only get two years of the
fruit. Now you could be sort of think that this might be
a case of מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzat. You owe me three years
of fruit, I only owe you two years of fruit. Let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says about this. Okay, וקדים מלווה ואכלינהו לפירא.
vekadim malveh ve'achlinhu lepeira. And the fruit of the third year, so
maybe they were debating it at in the third year, and before
it came to בית דין, Beis Din, so if they were the
מלווה malveh actually already consumed the fruit. You know, he sold it,
he pocketed it, he put it in his bank account, and now
the לווה loveh is coming to try to get that fruit out
of the possession of the מלווה, malveh, get his money back, claiming
that it was only two years that the מלווה malveh had rights
to it. Okay, וקדים מלווה ואכלינהו לפירא. vekadim malveh ve'achlinhu lepeira. מי
נאמן? Mi ne'eman? Who is believed? Okay, so do we say like
המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה? hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah? How do we understand
this? רב יהודה אמר קרקע בחזקת בעליה קיימא. Rav Yehuda amar karka
bechezkat be'aleha kayama. Okay, that the land is always considered to be
under the you know, in the possession, under the control of the
owner. And we had this before and actually the גמרא Gemara is
going to get back to the case before about a debate about
when you sold something for 12 months and for a whole year
and so on. We'll see about that. And that means that even
if the what do you call it, even if the case comes
to בית דין Beis Din later, we always go back to when
it was the קרקע karka itself and what the who would have
been considered the המוציא מחבירו. hamotzi mechavero. What does that mean? So
שמעון Shimon is the one who owns the land. So the land
is always considered right ראובן, Reuven, the guy who lent the money,
is the one who has the right to the פירות. peirot. So
the land is always considered to be in שמעון's Shimon possession. And
therefore, had the case come to בית דין Beis Din at the
beginning of the third year, we would have said המוציא מחבירו עליו
הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. The land is in שמעון's Shimon possession.
If ראובן Reuven wants to get the fruit and the benefit of
this next year, he's trying to take something away from שמעון, Shimon,
he has the burden of proof. And the חידוש, chiddush, okay, that
would have been if it had come in the beginning of the
third year, but it came at the end and ראובן Reuven already
took and sold the fruit. But what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is
saying is, it doesn't matter.
Since originally שמעון Shimon would have been the one who we would
assume it was in his that... It would have been seen in
his possession, and ראובן Reuven was trying to take it away from
שמעון, Shimon, the burden of proof always rests on ראובן, Reuven, even
if ראובן Reuven now has pocketed the money. Okay, so if ראובן
Reuven can't prove that it's at three, he's got to give the
money back to שמעון. Shimon. קרקע בחזקת בעליה קיימי. Karka bechezkas ba'aleha
kaimei. רב כהנא Rav Kahana says,
no, פירות בחזקת אוכליהן קיימי. peiros bechezkas ochleihen kaimei. No, the fruit
is in the hands of who ate them. So meaning that practically
now, ראובן Reuven has already consumed the fruit. So בית דין beis
din would have to come and try to get ראובן Reuven to
pay. So that is always the question of how do you define
who is the מוציא מחבירו, motzi mechaveiro, not how it was originally,
how we would have defined it, but right now, right now בית
דין beis din has to get the money out of ראובן's Reuven
hand. So שמעון, Shimon, because ראובן Reuven already ate the fruit, so
שמעון Shimon is the מוציא מחבירו motzi mechaveiro and therefore שמעון Shimon
has the burden of proof. Okay, so it's an interesting conceptual question
whether המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechaveiro alav haraaya is measured by,
you know, sort of like status quo and therefore if you want
to change the status quo, you have the burden of proof and
who will בית דין beis din have to act against? And then
you would say, okay, בית דין beis din is going to have
to act against ראובן, Reuven, he's eaten the fruit. שמעון Shimon is
the מוציא מחבירו. motzi mechaveiro. Or do you say מוציא מחבירו motzi
mechaveiro means there's like a presumption of ownership based on who the
מוחזק muchzak was? And if that's true, that's רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda
statement. Since שמעון Shimon was the מוחזק, muchzak, that created a presumption
of ownership and even once ראובן Reuven took the fruit, ראובן Reuven
is still being מוציא motzi from שמעון Shimon and ראובן Reuven has
the burden of proof. So that's a very nice conceptual debate. And
the גמרא Gemara says הלכתא כוותיה דרב כהנא. hilchesa kevasei deRav Kahana.
We rule like רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, דאמר פירות בחזקת אוכליהן. deamar
peiros bechezkas ochleihen. That no, we look at the status quo, status
quo is now ראובן Reuven has eaten the fruit, שמעון Shimon is
the מוציא מחבירו, motzi mechaveiro, so he can't prove it, he's out
of luck. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, וקיימא לן דהלכתא
כוותיה דרב נחמן. v'kaima lan dehilchesa kevasei deRav Nachman. But we said
earlier that in a seemingly identical debate, that we rule like רב
נחמן Rav Nachman דאמר קרקע בחזקת בעליה עומדת. deamar karka bechezkas ba'aleha
omedes. That says that you go by the land and not by
who's right now in possession. Now to remind you what that case
was, was it was a case where you sold the the house
was rented and it was said it's going to be twelve dollars
for the year or whatever, twelve hundred dollars for the year, a
hundred dollars per month. And then it wound up that it was
a leap year and there were thirteen months. So does the renter,
does the tenant, let's say, have to pay for that extra month?
So you know, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said yes, he's
the מוציא מחבירו, motzi mechaveiro, the landlord has the possession of, you
know, owns the land, so the tenant wants to get the use
of it away from the landlord, he has the burden of proof.
And he says even if the money is still in his pocket,
is still in the tenant's pocket, and even if it's at the
end of the month that he's already benefited from the use of
that property for a month, still he has the burden of proof
and he has to go ahead and pay the landlord because originally
when that issue came up, the land was in the possession of
ראובן, Reuven, of the landlord, he was considered to be presumed to
be, you know, the rightful owner. And even after שמעון Shimon has
taken it and pocketed it and so on and been in it
for the month, he still has the burden of proof. So that
seems to be the
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda position. You go by
the owner of the land when the issue first came up, not
like the status quo right now. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
התם מילתא דלא עבידא לאיגלויי היא, הכא מילתא דעבידא לאיגלויי. hasam milsa
d'lo avid l'igluyei hee, hacha milsa d'avid l'igluyei.
There,
we're never going to find out what the deal actually was. Right?
There it says twelve months, twelve hundred dollars for the year, a
hundred dollars per month. There is the document is
itself like winds up being self-contradictory and there's no more evidence to
be brought, you know, nobody claims anything else was said. So when
it's going to remain a question and there's no way it'll ever
get resolved, בית דין beis din won't have to reverse themselves. So
if בית דין beis din isn't concerned about reversing themselves, then we're
going to rule like רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Then we're going to
say it doesn't matter right now who's pocketing it, you go by
the קרקע. karka. And since originally the קרקע, karka, you know, was
in the possession of the landlord, even if שמעון Shimon has already
been in it for that month, שמעון's Shimon got to pay. And
we're not afraid that שמעון Shimon is going to, that we're going
to ever have to take the money back away from ראובן Reuven
and give it to שמעון, Shimon, because no more evidence can come
to light. But הכא מילתא דעבידא לאיגלויי היא. hacha milsa d'avid l'igluyei
hee. In this case, which just said years and you don't know
if it was two or three, so maybe witnesses will come and
they'll testify to what the original arrangement was. So more evidence might
come to the fore, ואטרוחי בי דינא תרי זימני לא מטרחינן. v'atruchei
beis dina trei zimni lo matrchinen. And we do not make בית
דין beis din go to the effort twice. So meaning here It
just said years. If you go ahead and say,
the לוה, Loveh, the person whose land it was, he's always considered
in possession, and even though the מלווה Malveh has eaten the fruit,
he's got to pay the money back to the לוה Loveh because
it was always the land was always in the לוה's Loveh possession,
then if more evidence comes to light and we prove that it
was three years, בית דין Beis Din is going to have to
have another court case and have him give it back to the
מלווה. Malveh. So in that case where we might wind up reversing
ourselves, that's where we say status quo, that we will not disturb
the status quo unless you can prove it. That's המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya in terms of not disturbing the status
quo. If you want us בית דין Beis Din to act, you've
got to go ahead and prove it. So that would be to
that's the case when we might have to reverse ourselves. So then
we're not going to move now if we might have to just
reverse ourselves later. In a case where we know we won't have
to reverse ourselves, then we can be more conceptual about המוציא מחברו
Hamotzi mechavero and the קרקע karka was always in the possession of
its owner and not just ask who has already pocketed the money
now or not. Okay, that's a very nice distinction.
Okay.
מלווה אומר חמש לוה אומר שלש. Malveh omer chamesh, Loveh omer shalosh.
So now, it just says years again and the מלווה Malveh says
I had five years rights to it and the לוה Loveh says
you only had three. It's interesting the לוה Loveh could have said
two because the minimum of years is
two. So אמר
ליה אייתי לי שטרך. Amar lei ayisli shtarchah. So the לוה Loveh
says to the
מלווה, Malveh, go bring me the document that shows
that the debt document that says I owe you a thousand dollars
and that you have rights
to five years. So it actually seems not like I just said
a minute ago, not like the document said years but it didn't
say how many. They actually have lost the loan document. Okay and
the loan document presumably also said you borrowed ten thousand dollars and
he has rights for x number of years. So they've lost the
loan document but nobody is disputing the loan. They're just disputing how
many years the מלווה Malveh had rights to it. So the לוה
Loveh says to the מלווה, Malveh, שמעון Shimon says to ראובן, Reuven,
you say five years? Go bring me the loan document and let's
see how many years it says in it because I'm saying you
only had three years rights. Okay. אייתי לי שטרך. Ayisli shtarchah. אמר
ליה שטרא אירכס לי. Amar lei shtra irkas li. I lost it.
All right. אמר רב יהודה מלווה נאמן. Amar Rav Yehuda Malveh ne'eman.
The מלווה Malveh is believed. מיגו דאי בעי אמר לקוחה היא בידי
Migo de'ei ba'ei amar lekucha hi beyadi
because he could have said I already purchased it. I've already been
on it three years. So what's now is becoming clear that the
מלווה Malveh has already been on it three years, right? Otherwise the
לוה Loveh could have had a מיגו. migo. He said three, I
could have said two, I could have said one. But the מלווה
Malveh has been on it three years. So the לוה Loveh says
time for you to get off, three years have been paid. The
מלווה Malveh says what do you mean? I have two extra years.
So even though he can't prove it with a שטר shtar and
again we should say קרקע בחזקת בעליה עומדת, karka bechezkat ba'aleha omedet,
right? It's in the possession of the owner, of the borrower, of
שמעון. Shimon. The מלווה Malveh is making a claim that he's entitled
for two more years. Why should he be believed? He hasn't even
pocketed it yet, only three years are up. So we should totally
believe the לוה. Loveh. But רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says no, the
מלווה Malveh is believed because he says look I've been on it
three years. I could just claim I bought it. And that's a
whole בבא בתרא Bava Batra סוגיא. sugya. If somebody's been on land
three years and claims that they've bought it and the original owner
has not been making any protests over the course of the three
years, he's believed because he doesn't have to hold on to his
bill of sale for forever. So once he's been on it three
years and there have been no protests registered, so the מלווה Malveh
could have said look you never registered a protest and if I
wanted to I could just say I purchased it. So therefore you
should believe me when I say that I'm entitled to two more
years. Okay so this only works in a scenario that he's been
on it for three years. Okay and even though we should side
with the לוה Loveh because קרקע בחזקת בעליה, karka bechezkat ba'aleha, the
מלווה Malveh has a מיגו. migo. אמר רב יהודה מלווה נאמן מיגו
דאי בעי אמר לקוחה היא בידי. Amar Rav Yehuda Malveh ne'eman migo
de'ei ba'ei amar lekucha hi beyadi. אמר ליה רב פפא לרב אשי.
Amar lei Rav Pappa le'Rav Ashi. רב פפא Rav Pappa said to
רב אשי. Rav Ashi. רב זביד ורב אבירא לא סבירא להו הא
דרב יהודה. Rav Zvid ve'Rav Avira lo sevira lehu ha de'Rav Yehuda.
I don't get it. Don't...
hold on. I read that wrong, it was not a question, it
was a statement. So אמר ליה רב פפא לרב אשי. Amar lei
Rav Pappa le'Rav Ashi. So רב פפא Rav Pappa said to רב
אשי. Rav Ashi. רב זביד ורב אבירא לא סבירא להו הא דרב
יהודה. Rav Zvid ve'Rav Avira lo sevira lehu ha de'Rav Yehuda. They
don't hold of this idea of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that you
have a מיגו migo in this case. Why not? מאי טעמא האי
שטרא כיון דלגוביינא קאי מיזהר זהיר ביה ומכבש הוא דכבשיה לשטריה. Mai
ta'ama hai shtra keivan d'leguveyina kai mizhar zahir bei umichbash hu dechavshei
leshtarei. So the מלווה, Malveh, the שטר, shtar, remember is the שטר
shtar that says how many years the מלווה Malveh has rights to
it. But it's also the basic document of the loan. He borrowed
ten thousand dollars. He's going to use this to prove that the
guy owes him ten thousand dollars. So he says the מלווה Malveh
since it is standing there to give him the rights to collect
the loan or to give him the rights to use the פירות
peirot for x number of years, he obviously is going to be
very careful with it. Okay. And it's not like by the way
I just mentioned a minute ago that a bill of sale you
don't have to hold on to more than three years, like how
long do you have to hold on to your tax documents? But
a bill of sale, you're not going to... planning on using, you
know, it's just if you're ever challenged. If nobody challenged you in
three years, you stop paying attention. But he's saying a loan document,
the מלווה malveh always knows he's got to have it ready to
be able to use to collect his loan if the guy ever
denies the loan. So therefore כיון דלגוביינא קאי, keivan dilguvaina kai, since
it's going to be used to collect the loan, מזדהר זהר ביה,
mizdehar zehar bei, the מלווה malveh is always very careful with it.
ומיחזי umi-chazi so therefore when he says, "Whoops, I lost it," that
already makes our eyebrows go up. We become skeptical. ומכבש הוא דכבשיה
לשטרא, umichbash hu dikavshei l'shtara,
he's really just hiding the שטר, shtar, okay, there's no way he
lost it. So when he's saying he can't produce it, what it
really it really that makes us think that if he that he's
lying and if he did produce it, it would back up the
לוה. loveh. Okay, סבר אוכלה תרתין שנין יתירתא, savar ochla tartin shanin
yetirata,
he figures I'll hide the שטר shtar and claim I had it
for five years and I'll eat two extra years. So what does
that mean? Why does the מיגו migo not work? Couldn't he still
say לקוחה היא בידי, lekucha hi beyadi, you know, even against your
claim that he oh obviously he's lying? So that becomes an idea
like of מיגו במקום עדים. migo b'makom edim. Not עדים edim but
like, you know, we don't believe a מיגו migo when we feel
that there's blatant evidence against it. So a מיגו, migo, you know,
I could have said that I bought it so you should believe
me now that I said that I lost the שטר. shtar. By
the way, you're believing him two things: you're believing him A, that
he lost the שטר, shtar, and B, you know, that it actually
said five, that's against the לוה's loveh חזקה. chazakah. So that's a
lot of work that a מיגו migo has to do to be
מוציא motzi from the לוה's loveh חזקה, chazakah, and we're not prepared
to do that in a case that's מיגו להוציא migo lehotzi also,
and we're not prepared to do that in a case where we
really think that the statement is clearly false. Okay, so they refuse
to accept that, even with the מיגו. migo. אמר ליה רבינא לרב
אשי, amar leh Ravina l'Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, so if that's true that
that that מיגו migo doesn't work, אלא מעתה האי משכנתא דסורא דכתבי
הכי, ela me'ata hai mashkanta de-Sura dichitvi hachi, so this classic משכנתא
דסורא mashkanta de-Sura which is what we've been talking about, which is
a mortgage that you get the benefit for X number of years
and then the loan is paid off. And what's written in it
is, במשלם שניא אילן תיפוק ארעא דא בלא כסף. b'mishlam shanya ilen
tipuk ara da bela kesaf. At the end of these years, five
years, three years, whatever the duration is, then the land goes back
to the owner without ever having to pay the loan because the
use of it for these X number of years was the payment
of the loan. So I got a question. I mean, that's exactly
our scenario, okay? But he says, wait a minute. He says, I
don't even understand something. When you mentioned this מיגו, migo, you said
he could claim that it was
purchased. So isn't that always going to be a problem? How does
this work? The מלווה malveh gets the document that says Shimon owes
ten thousand dollars and it says that he has the right that
ראובן's Reuven got the right to get the פירות peiros for X
number of years, okay? I don't get it. Why can't ראובן Reuven
just at the end of three years conveniently lose the שטר shtar
and not even talk about the שטר shtar and just say לקוחה
היא בידי? lekucha hi beyadi? I mean, isn't this going to be
exposed to tremendous abuse? The guy is on the land, he's eating
the פירות. peiros. How are we going to stop every single person
in a case of this mortgage, every single מלווה malveh from just
claiming that they've purchased it after they've been there for three years?
So it's not like anything you said before
was particularly the assumption you're making that he could say לקוחה. lekucha.
He says, I don't get it, if that's true, we got a
big we got a bigger problem here. Okay. היכא דכבשיה לשטרא במשכנתא,
heicha dikavshei l'shtara b'mashkanta,
so in any case where the מלווה malveh decides to hide the
שטר shtar ואמר לקוחה היא בידי, ve-amar lekucha hi beyadi, הכי נמי
דמהימן, hachi nami de-meheiman, would he be believed? So the fact that
you said he could say it, that's a shocker to me. I
always assumed that there was something that was not going to let
him say it. We'll see what that is in a minute. And
but you know, that there would have been a reason he wouldn't
be believed. But if you're saying he can, how are you preventing
this tremendous abuse? Every lender will just say that לקוחה היא בידי
lekucha hi beyadi after three years. וכי מתקני רבנן מילתא דאתי בה
לידי פסידא? ve-chi matkini rabanan milta de-ati bah lidei pesida? The Rabbis
were back the whole idea of the of the משכנתא דסורא. mashkanta
de-Sura. How would they do this if it could completely be you
know be tremendously abused, misused? Okay. אמר ליה לא התם תקינו ליה
רבנן דמרי ארעא יהיב תסקא amar leh lo hatam tikinu leh rabanan
demarei ara yaheiv tiska וכרי
כריא. ve-charei charya. So it says, no no no, that's not a
problem, because they established that in a case of משכנתא דסורא, mashkanta
de-Sura, the owner, the borrower who owns the land, would be the
one that would pay the property tax and he would be the
one that would like dig the holes that or the trenches you
would have to dig each year. So therefore there would never you
know you wouldn't be concerned that that would make it clear that
he's the owner and there would be no way that the creditor
could say לקוחה היא בידי. lekucha hi beyadi. So the גמרא Gemara
says, that's nice when it works, ארעא דלית בה כריא ולא יהיב
תסקא מאי, ara de-leisa bei charya velo yaheiv tiska mai, and if
it's a land that you don't have to dig ditches and you
don't. He'd have to dig ditches here. So therefore, there would never,
that would make it clear that he's the owner and there would
be no way that the creditor could say לקוחה היא בידי. lakucha
hi beyadi. So the גמרא Gemara says, that's nice when it works,
ארעא דלית כריא ולא יהיב כסמא ara delaise karia velo yaise kismaye
and if it's a land that you don't have to dig ditches
and you don't have to pay a property tax, what do we
do? How we're protecting the owner? אמר ליה איבעי ליה למחויי. amar
lei ibei lei lemichuyei. He could do a מחאה, machaah, okay, which
is always the answer, right? If somebody's on your land and you
don't want them to claim that it's purchased, you have to do
a מחאה. machaah. Now why did we not think, you have to
get up and do a protest and say I want to let
it known that that guy's on my land, but it's not his,
he's only there as a
creditor and it's a mortgage property. So that's always the way that
you protect yourself, why was, did the גמרא Gemara not assume that?
Because the גמרא Gemara assumed that the classic מחאה machaah is that
you say this person is a גנב, ganav, okay, and you need
the provocation that somebody's on your land without any permission. And that
provocation makes you protest, and if you didn't protest, your silence is
evidence that he's the real owner. But here there's no provocation, like,
you know, he has the right to be there and get the
פירות. peiros. So we didn't think that מחאה machaah was meaningful, we
didn't think your silence was meaningful here because you're not really being
provoked. But the גמרא Gemara is saying no, no, no, if we're
going to allow a
משכנתא, mashkanta, then the debtors have to know, the owners of the
land have to know that they'd better make an annual מחאה machaah
to protect themselves from it being claimed that it's not, that it
was purchased by, you know, by the other guy. Okay, איבעי ליה
למחויי. ibei lei lemichuyei. לא אימחי מאי? lo imchi mai? And if
he doesn't do a מחאה, machaah, then how you protecting him? איהו
דאפסיד אנפשיה. ihu de-afsid anafshei. All right, you know, he is going
ahead and he is, that's his own, he, you know, he brought
the loss upon himself. So we introduced this idea, you know, the
question was, do you have a מיגו migu that he could have
said five years, and we said he didn't have a מיגו, migu,
he obviously didn't lose the שטר, shtar, but we introduced the question
about how does every person, every creditor who's with a משכנתא דסורא
mashkanta de-Sura not have the ability to just claim לקוחה היא בידי?
lakucha hi beyadi? And the answer is, the owner has to be
on the ball and has to do a מחאה. machaah. Okay. אריס
אומר למחצה ירדתי ובעל הבית אומר לשליש הורדתי. aris omer lemachetza yaradeti
uva'al habayis omer lishlish horadeti. Now
another question. So the sharecropper says, you know, I did the work
and the agreement was, was that I was going to get half,
and the בעל הבית ba'al habayis says no, no, no, you only,
it was the agreement was that you were only going to get
a third. Okay,
מי נאמן? mi ne'eman? Who's believed?
So
מי
נאמן? mi ne'eman? רב יהודה אמר בעל הבית נאמן, Rav Yehuda amar
ba'al habayis ne'eman, the בעל הבית ba'al habayis is believed. Okay, ורב
נחמן אמר הכל כמנהג המדינה. veRav Nachman amar hakol keminhag hamedina. So
why would he say the בעל הבית ba'al habayis is believed? Again,
קרקע בחזקת בעליה קיימי, karka bechezkas be'aleha kaymi, so the owner is
in the possession of the land, so
the sharecropper is the המוציא מחבירו. hamotzi mechavero. But, but רב נחמן
Rav Nachman says no, if there's a standard in the city, you
will assume the standard that works even against המוציא מחבירו, hamotzi mechavero,
unless there's evidence that you have done something against the standard practice,
then we assume that it was the standard practice. סברו מינה לא
פליגי. savru mina lo pligi.
We thought that they really weren't debating, that when, you know, in
a place it depended whether the normal practice was a half or
a third. The one who said the בעל הבית ba'al habayis is
believed to say a third, that was the normal practice. The one
who said the בעל הבית ba'al habayis was believed to say a
half, you know, excuse me, the אריס aris was believed to say
a half, that was where that was the normal practice. Okay, so
then it's really not a question of מי נאמן, mi ne'eman, then
it's really everybody's just saying הכל כמנהג המדינה. hakol keminhag hamedina. Okay,
so it didn't really sound like that. It sounded like there was
a debate. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. הא באתרא דשקיל
אריסא פלגא הא באתרא דשקיל אריסא תילתא. ha be'asra deshakeil arisa palga
ha be'asra deshakeil arisa silsa. אמר להו רב מרי בריה דבת שמואל,
amar lehu Rav Mari berei de-bas Shmuel, no. So הכי אמר אביי,
hachi amar Abaye, אפילו באתרא דשקיל אריסא פלגא פליגי, afilu be'asra deshakeil
arisa palga pligi, that's not true. Even in a case where the
אריס aris normally gets a half, you know רב נחמן Rav Nachman
says, excuse me, not רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
says, again, this is the רב יהודה Rav Yehuda of קרקע בחזקת
בעליה קיימי, karka bechezkas be'aleha kaymi, that even against the מנהג המדינה,
minhag hamedina, if the אריס aris wants to get out of the
hands of the בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, so even though the standard
is a half, the בעל הבית ba'al habayis is the מוחזק, muchzak,
קרקע בחזקת בעליה, karka bechezkas be'aleha, and therefore the אריס aris is
still המוציא מחבירו. hamotzi mechavero. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda really takes
this קרקע בחזקת בעליה, karka bechezkas be'aleha, you know, so strong even
against הכל כמנהג המדינה. hakol keminhag hamedina. פליגי. pligi. רב יהודה אמר
בעל הבית נאמן דאי בעי אמר שכירי ולקיטי הוא. Rav Yehuda amar
ba'al habayis ne'eman de-i ba'ei amar sechiri ulekiti hu.
Now the last line of the גמרא Gemara does not make it
based on the principle before of קרקע בחזקת בעליה, karka bechezkas be'aleha,
it seems to go back to the type of מיגו migu argument
you know that we had as well that we had before. That
why is he believed? Because he could say, so maybe you're right,
maybe the מנהג המדינה minhag hamedina would make it clear and that
would be strong enough against מוחזק muchzak and המוציא מחבירו. hamotzi mechavero.
But you have a מיגו migu here, because you could always say
when it's not a sharecropping, they're day laborers, and I pay them
by the day, and I only owe them today's wages. So if
there's no document and no way to prove that they're sharecroppers, that
is going to give נאמנות ne'emanus to the
בעל הבית ba'al habayis because he. Now one wonders, you know, what
about in all these cases, the משכנתא, mashkanta, this case, etc., when
claims could be made, let's say there's it's there's a perception in
the town and everybody knows and it's taken for granted that they're
sharecroppers and they've always been sharecroppers and so on, you know, maybe
that would change it. Okay. יתומים אומרים אנו השבחנו ובעל חוב אומר
אביכם השביח. Yesomim omru anu hishbachnu u'ba'al chov omer avichem hishbiach. So,
another case where there's a debate and no evidence. So
Shimon dies, Reuven is coming to collect the thousand dollars that Reuven
owed him, and he can only collect from the property that Reuven
left to his יתומים, yesomim, okay, to his children. Now,
the principle is that if the land was, now, let's say when
the loan was taken out, the thousand dollar loan, this piece of
property was worth a thousand dollars.
Now improvements have been made and it's worth twelve hundred. So the
question is who made the improvements? If Reuven made the improvements, then
you know, the בעל חוב ba'al chov is entitled to, you know,
to collect it.
So, you know, and whatever, he might have to pay back the
difference or whatever, we'll see about that, but you know, but he's
entitled to collect it.
If
the orphans made the improvements, then it was nothing that the original
בעל חוב ba'al chov had a lien upon, and therefore he's not
entitled. So let's take a look and we'll see actually also about
whether it equals the loan or exceeds the loan, let's take a
look. But the bottom line is is that the בעל חוב ba'al
chov is not entitled to any improvements that the orphans made, only
to the things that were that the father made and that he
had a lien upon in the father's life. So סבר רב חנינא
למימר savar Rav Chanina l'meimar top of ק"י עמוד ב'. kuf yud
amud bais. So Rav Chanina thought to say, ארעא בחזקת יתמי קיימא
ובעל חוב עליו ראיה. ara b'chezkat yasmi kaimei u'ba'al chov alav raya.
We're going back to this idea of whose חזקה chazaka is it
in? The land is in the חזקה chazaka is in the possession
of the orphans, and it's the creditor who has to prove that
the improvements were made while the father was still alive. אמר להו
ההוא סבא, amar lehu hahu saba, so a certain elder said, הכי
אמר ר' יוחנן, hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan, no, here's what Rabbi Yochanan
said. על היתומים להביא ראיה. al hayesomim l'havi raya. No, the orphans
have to bring it. Why? מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason?
ארעא כיון דלגוביינא קיימא כמאן דגביא דמי ועל היתומים להביא ראיה. ara
keivan d'leguvayna kaimei k'man d'gavya dami v'al hayesomim l'havi raya.
Since this land was had a lien on it, it's like it's
already been collected, meaning who is considered whose possession is it considered
to be in? It's considered to be in the creditor's possession because
the creditor has a lien. Now later the גמרא Gemara is going
to say it's a case of an אפותיקי. apotiki. אפותיקי Apotiki means
a specific lien that this is the only property I collect from.
And that makes it considered already partially owned by the creditor, by
the מלווה. malveh. Okay, so but that's what he is saying. Because
of those liens that the מלווה malveh has, he's the one who
the property is considered to be in the possession of. Yes, קרקע
בחזקת בעליה, karka b'chezkat ba'aleha, but the מלווה malveh is considered to
be the בעליה ba'aleha here because of his lien and the orphans
have to go ahead and prove that they were the ones that
made the benefit, not the מלווה. malveh. Now you remember before, we
were talking about a whole case of a mortgage and a משכנתא
mashkanta and so on and the original owner was considered to be
the one whose control it was in, not the מלווה. malveh. So
again, the גמרא Gemara here is going to make it a very
particular type of a lien, a lien of an אפותיקי. apotiki. But
let's keep on going. Okay. אמר אביי אף אנן נמי תנינא.
amar Abaye af anan
nami tanina. We taught similarly. ספק זה קדם וספק זה קדם קוצץ
ואינו נותן דמים. safek zeh kadam v'safek zeh kadam kotzetz v'eino nosen
damim.
So if basically this is a case where
a
tree is planted within fifty אמות, amos, an אמה amah is about
a foot and a half, seventy-five feet of the outer boundaries of
the city. And the rule is that you want it to have
the area right outside of the city clear without trees, but if
the tree was planted after the city was there, then you know,
then you cut it down and you don't pay the owner. If
the tree was planted before the city was there, then you cut
it down and you do pay the owner. Okay, let's say you
don't know. So ספק זה קדם ספק זה קדם, safek zeh kadam
safek zeh kadam, you don't know which came first, the city or
the tree. קוצץ, kotzetz, so either way you're going to cut it
down. ואינו נותן דמים, v'eino nosen damim, and you don't pay the
money. Why not? Why don't we say that like the tree is
in the possession of the owner and you're המוציא מחברו, hamotzi mechavero,
you know, if you want to cut it down and therefore you
have to pay him the money? אלמא, alma, what we see from
this is, כיון דלמיקץ קאי, keivan d'lemikatz kai, since one way either
way you're going to cut the tree down, אמינא ליה אייתי ראיה
ושקול. amina lei ayisi raya u'shkol. So we don't say the tree
is in the possession of the owner, you want to cut it
down, pay me. Either way we're going to cut it down. The
only question is do we pay you or not. So we cut
it down and then you want to get the money from us,
you're the המוציא מחברו. hamotzi mechavero. So הכא נמי, hacha nami, here
too, האי שטרא כיון דלגוביינא קאי, hai shtra keivan d'leguvayna kai, this
document since... since you're definitely going to use it to collect and
you're going to collect from this piece of property, okay, again, it's
a specifically this piece of property, כמאן דגביא דמי, keman degavya dami,
it's like it's already collected, and so it's the קרקע karka land
is in the possession of the what do you call it, of
the you know of the of the מלווה. malve. By the way,
the משכנתא דסורא, mashkanta desura, besides not being an אפותיקי, apotiki, in
the specific case of the משכנתא דסורא, mashkanta desura, the land goes
back right sorry to the original owner. So that definitely is not
a case of a lien that's going to ultimately be collected. Okay,
but here you have a lien that's going to be collected and
maybe very specifically the loan is going to collect only from this
קרקע, karka, and that makes it under the possession of the מלווה.
malve. והיתומים לאו בני ראיה. ve'hayetomim lav benei raya. Okay, now now
we're going to see about this question about you know how much
was the loan and how much was the שבח shevach and how
that all fits works out. Let's take a look. אייתי יתמי ראיה
דאינהו אשבחו. ayti yatmi raya de'inhu ashbachu. Let's say then okay so
the orphans actually brought proof that they were the ones that improved
it.
סבר רבי חנינא למימר כי מסלקינן להו בארעא מסלקינן להו. savar Rabbi
Chanina lemeimar ki mesalkinan lehu be'ara mesalkinan lehu. Okay, so now you
are so because of that so it it seems like the following.
It seems I might have misstated this earlier, apologies. It seems like
the following. It seems like the lien was only for let's say
he borrowed a thousand dollars, the lien was for eight hundred and
the land was worth eight hundred.
If the father improved the two hundred then okay the creditor is
entitled to take the whole plot of land worth a thousand, pays
the loan. If the orphans improved it, there was no lien on
what the orphans improved and the creditor can take the only can
take eight hundred dollars out of it, he's out his other two
hundred dollars. Ah, the father owes him two hundred dollars? Sorry, you
can only collect those two hundred dollars on something you have a
lien on and you don't have a lien on the extra two
hundred dollars that was created by the orphans. Okay, so in that
case the creditor is just going to be out. So fine, but
that
was done okay, the orphans proved that the two hundred extra dollars
were by them and therefore the creditor only had a lien on
eight hundred dollars, he can only collect eight hundred dollars of the
loan. Now how does he collect it? Does he take the whole
plot of land and pay them back two hundred dollars in cash
or does he have to give them a two hundred dollar piece
of the land? All right so let's take a look. סבר רבי
חנינא למימר כי מסלקינן להו בארעא מסלקינן להו. savar Rabbi Chanina lemeimar
ki mesalkinan lehu be'ara mesalkinan lehu.
Now that the creditor is going to take the plot of land
he has to give two hundred dollars back to the orphans, he
has to give them twenty percent of the land, he has to
give them a plot of the land, he can only take eight
hundred dollars out of the land because his liens in the life
of the father was only eight hundred dollars. ולא היא velo hi
and that's not the הלכה. halacha. בדמי מסלקינן להו. bidmei mesalkinan lehu.
Actually he's entitled to take the whole plot of land, you don't
force him to break up the plot of land and he gives
the orphans back two hundred dollars because his liens were only eight
hundred dollars. מדרב נחמן miderav Nachman from what Rav Nachman said. דאמר
רב נחמן אמר שמואל שלשה שמין להם את השבח ומעלין אותם בדמים.
de'amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel shelosha shamin lahem et hashevach uma'alin otam
bidamim. Three people you you evaluate you value the the cost of
the improvements, they're not entitled to the improvements that were made on
the land, but they get the whole land and they just pay
the person the cash value, which makes sense. You don't want to
break up a piece of land. All right. So who are these
three people? ואלו הן בכור לפשוט. ve'elu hen bechor lepashut. A a
you know a firstborn son to a normal son. So what does
this mean? בכור bechor firstborn gets two portions. So let's say there's
just two sons, a firstborn and a second born. We'll call it
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon conveniently. So ראובן, Reuven, you divide the
land into three portions, ראובן Reuven gets two and שמעון Shimon gets
one. Now while they are you know
before the property has been divided and after the father died, they're
making capital improvements on the land. All right. And they've both chipped
in and they've made capital improvements or or let's just you know
say whatever, let's just say that שמעון Shimon made all the capital
improvements. Now they're going to divide the land and ראובן Reuven is
going to take his two-thirds of it. All right.
Now we got a question though. But שמעון Shimon says but שמעון
Shimon says to him, hey that's very nice you just took two-thirds
of of the property our father left us, but a thousand dollars
were my capital improvements, I want a thousand dollars of land from
your two-thirds. And the answer is no. He's entitled to two-thirds of
the real estate the proper the father left and if those contain
and are worth more because of improvements
that שמעון Shimon made, ראובן Reuven is able to pay him in
cash. Does not have to give him land. Okay, that's בכור לפשוט.
bechor lepashut. בעל חוב וכתובת אשה ליתומים. ba'al chov uchetuvat isha leyetomim.
And this is our case. Okay, orphans, you have either a a
creditor or a woman. a wife collecting her כתובה kesubah debt from
the orphans, so again, even when the orphans definitely made improvements, that
doesn't mean that they now can claim a piece of the land.
They get the land that had the liens on it, and they
pay the orphans back the cash for their improvement. ובעל חוב ללקוחות.
u'ba'al chov le'lakuchos.
And similarly if you've got a what do you call it, a
creditor and purchasers.
So ראובן Reuven had a lien on שמעון's Shimon land. שמעון Shimon
went ahead and sold it to לוי. Levi. If לוי Levi made
capital improvements, when ראובן Reuven comes to collect the land that was
now sold to לוי, Levi, he gets the whole plot of land
and he gives לוי Levi back the improvements that לוי Levi made.
And in all of those again, it makes sense, you have a
lien, you have rights, etc., and we don't want to force you
to break up the land, you just pay the person for the
capital improvement. All right, so אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי. amar lei
Ravina le-Rav Ashi. So רבינא Ravina said to
רב אשי. Rav Ashi. למימרא דסבר שמואל בעל חוב ללקוחות יהיב שבחא.
lemeimra de-savar Shmuel ba'al chov le-lakuchos yaiv shvacha. So when a בעל
חוב ba'al chov comes to collect
from the purchasers, he has to pay back for the improvements
that the purchasers made. And again, when he had a lien on
שמעון's Shimon land, שמעון Shimon sold it to לוי, Levi, לוי Levi
made improvements, so you're saying he can pay לוי Levi for the
improvements in cash, he doesn't have to give לוי Levi land. Okay,
but you're assuming that he's got to pay לוי Levi for the
improvements. Is that so obvious? ומי אית ליה שבחא ללוקח? umi is
lei shvacha le-lokeiach? Is that really true that the purchaser who makes
improvements is entitled to get that money back? I mean it makes
sense he's entitled to get that money back, let's see why not.
והאמר שמואל בעל חוב גובה את השבח. ve-ha-amar Shmuel ba'al chov goveh
es ha-shvach. That a the creditor when he comes to collect the
land, collects the land even with the improvements, capital improvements. He doesn't
pay back the capital improvement. Okay. וכי
תימא לא קשיא כאן בשבח המגיע לכתפים כאן בשבח שאינו מגיע לכתפים.
v'chi teima lo kashya kan b'shvach ha-magia le-ksafayim kan b'shvach she'eino magia
le-ksafayim.
Maybe it makes a difference between
whether the improvements and here we're assuming the improvement I've been saying
capital improvements, but let's say the שבח shvach is that he's the
purchaser has literally
planted wheat in it. So maybe it makes a difference how far
along the wheat is. If the wheat is up to the shoulders
or it's beyond the shoulders. Why does that matter? Because if it
is that far developed that it's already up to the shoulders, then
it's really not considered to be as one piece with the land.
So maybe when do you have to pay back the שבח shvach
when it's considered to be somewhat separate from the land. It's not
yet פירות, peiros, it's not yet considered fully grown fruit and completely
conceptually distinct, it's still שבח, shvach, an improved land, but it's not
tightly bound to the land. So maybe maybe שמואל Shmuel makes that
distinction and when it's not tightly bound to the land that's the
case he's saying that you have to pay. So one minute he
says והא מעשים בכל יום וקא מגבי שמואל אפילו בשבח
המגיע לכתפים. ve-ha ma'asim be-chol yom ve-ka magbi Shmuel afilu be-shvach ha-magia
le-ksafayim. But we know that no, שמואל Shmuel allows the בעל חוב
ba'al chov to collect even when the improvements, even when the wheat
has grown up to the shoulder height. So שמואל Shmuel says you
don't have to pay back for the שבח. shvach. So what's going
on here? Do you have to pay back for the שבח shvach
that the לוקח lokeiach makes or not? It's actually hard to understand
why you wouldn't have to pay back, the לוקח lokeiach put in
money out of his own pocket. So what's going on? So let's
take a look. לא קשיא הא דמסיק ביה כשיעור ארעא ושבחא הא
דלא מסיק ביה כשיעור ארעא ושבחא. lo kashya ha d'masik bei k'shiur
ara u'shvacha ha d'lo masik bei k'shiur ara u'shvacha. So the question
is and this gets back to what I was saying before in
the case of יתומים, yesomim, how much is the loan for? So
if the loan is for a thousand dollars and the land plus
the שבח, shvach, the land is worth eight hundred plus the שבח
shvach is two hundred, it's a thousand, then he can say I
had a thousand dollar lien on this property, it's true you the
לוקח lokeiach bought it when it was only eight hundred dollars and
you invested two hundred, but I have a thousand dollar lien and
I'm entitled to collect a thousand dollars out of it. And in
that case you don't pay back the שבח. shvach. When do you
pay back the שבח? shvach? You pay back the שבח shvach when
the the lien was for a thousand, the the land was worth
a thousand, and the שבח shvach was now worth an extra two
hundred. In that case you're only entitled to a thousand, so you
gotta pay back the two hundred. Okay?
So let's see that again. הא דמסיק ביה כשיעור ארעא ושבחא. ha
d'masik bei k'shiur ara u'shvacha. One case is that he has loaned
out to him the cost of the land plus the שבח. shvach.
In that case he takes the whole thing and he doesn't pay
the לוקח lokeiach anything and the לוקח lokeiach has to know that's
the risk he's undertaking and that's his loss. והא דלא מסיק ביה
כשיעור ארעא ושבחא, ve-ha d'lo masik bei k'shiur ara u'shvacha, but in
the other case when the שבח shvach the land itself is the
cost of the loan and the שבח shvach is on the top
of that, then he doesn't have to divide up the plot, he
gets the whole thing. plot of land and he pays back the
purchaser the increase in value. So now the גמרא Gemara is still
not done. וכי לא מסיק שיעור ארעא ושבחא, v'chi lo masik shi'ur
ar'a u'shvacha, even in the case where the loan is not worth
the land plus the שבח. shevach. It's only worth the value of
the land, the שבח shevach goes beyond the value of the loan.
דהב ליה זוזי ללוקח ומסלק ליה, dehav lei zuzei l'lokeiach u'mesalik lei,
and then you're saying in that case, since the שבח shevach goes
beyond the value, he goes ahead
and he takes the whole plot of land and he pays the
לוקח lokeiach with money. But one minute says the גמרא. Gemara. הניחא
למאן דאמר אי אית ליה זוזי ללוקח לא מצי מסלק ליה לבעל
חוב. haniucha l'man d'amar ei it lei zuzei l'lokeiach lo matzi mesalik
lei l'ba'al chov. So here's a question. ראובן Reuven goes to collect
his debt from the land he had a lien on when for
the loan for שמעון Shimon and now that land is owned by
לוי. Levi. So he's coming to seize that land he's got a
lien on. לוי Levi wants that land. Does לוי Levi have a
right to pay ראובן Reuven the $1,000 to prevent him from exercising
his liens? Okay, so that's the question. So if you say אי
אית ליה זוזי ללוקח לא מצי מסלק ליה לבעל חוב, ei it
lei zuzei l'lokeiach lo matzi mesalik lei l'ba'al chov, that לוי Levi
cannot prevent ראובן Reuven from exercising his liens, then it makes sense.
ראובן Reuven exercises his liens, gets this plot of land that was
originally worth a thousand, now it's worth 1,200 thanks to לוי, Levi,
and he pays לוי Levi the $200. That's fine.
שפיר, shappir, that makes sense. אלא למאן דאמר אית ליה זוזי ללוקח
מצי מסלק ליה לבעל חוב, ella l'man d'amar it lei zuzei l'lokeiach
matzi mesalik lei l'ba'al chov, but if the rule was that when
לוי Levi had money, לוי Levi could pay ראובן Reuven and stop
him from collecting the land and keep all the land to himself,
so if that's true, why can't he hold on to $200 worth
of that land? ונימא ליה, v'neima lei,
why can't לוי Levi say to ראובן, Reuven, אי הוו לי זוזי
ei havu li zuzei if I had the $1,000, הוה מסלקינא לך
מכולה ארעא, hava mesalkina lach mikulah ar'a, I could get you off
of the whole land. השתא דלית לי זוזי, hashta d'leit li zuzei,
so fine, I don't have the cash on me. You're going to
exercise your loans and you're going to take the plot of land,
but don't give me you're going to give me $200 cash. But
with that $200 cash I want to buy back $200 worth of
the land and keep you off of $200 of the land. השתא
דלית לי זוזי הב
לי גריווא דארעא בארעא שיעור שבחאי, hashta d'leit li zuzei hav li
griwa d'ara b'ara shi'ur shvachai,
give me at least a small plot of land in this land
worth my improvements, right? Why should you pay me $200 in cash
and be able to kick me off the land? That cash gives
me the right to still hold on to a $200 piece of
land. So the גמרא Gemara says no. הכא במאי עסקינן כגון דשויה
ניהליה אפותיקי, hacha b'mai askinan k'gon d'shavyei nihalei apotiki, דאמר ליה לא
יהא לך פרעון אלא מזו. d'amar lei lo yehei lach piraon ella
mizu. Okay, so this is again the special case, and it does
seem from this גמרא Gemara that it's only because of this last
point we had to say it, but רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
introduced this point much earlier as well to explain these rights that
the מלווה malveh has that it is a type of a lien
that is only the thing that can only be collected from is
this and nothing else. And that gives the מלווה malveh more ownership
over the plot of land and also that makes it not possible
for לוי Levi to kick him off even if לוי Levi has
cash, so he's able to collect the whole land and give לוי
Levi the cash difference. We move on now to the
next משנה. mishnah. המקבל שדה מחבירו לשבוע אחד, hamikabel sadeh mechavero l'shavua
echad, if somebody becomes a agrees to be a renter, not a
sharecropper, a tenant for a seven-year period, בשבוע אחד, beshavua echad, בשבע
מאות זוז besheva me'ot zuz for 700 זוז zuz
for the seven-year period, השביעית מן המנין. hashvi'it min haminyan.
So he said a seven-year period, that counts שמיטה, Shmita, includes שמיטה.
Shmita. קיבל הימנו שבע שנים בשבע מאות זוז kibel heimenu sheva shanim
besheva me'ot zuz
if he said I will be a tenant for seven years, not
for a שבוע, shavua, a seven-year period, but for seven years of
farming it for 700 זוז, zuz,
so in that case אין השביעית מן המנין ein hashvi'it min haminyan
then it's not included because then it's clear that you're not treating
this as like a week, a year-long week, you're saying seven years,
which means each year is a planting year. שכיר יום, sechir yom,
now
okay, so that really belongs to the previous thing. Now we completely
shift gears and we start talking about the הלכה halacha about the
obligation to pay your earners in the on the day that they
earn well immediately after they've earned their money. So in case of
day laborers, the תורה Torah has two פסוקים. psukim. One says לא
תבא עליו השמש, lo tavo alav hashemesh, ביומו תתן שכרו, beyomo titein
scharo, pay him during his day, ולא תבא עליו השמש v'lo tavo
alav hashemesh and do not allow the sun to set. So that
sounds so חז"ל Chazal understand that can't be he works for you
in the day then you don't have any time to pay him.
So it must mean that ולא תבא עליו השמש v'lo tavo alav
hashemesh is a case where he's worked at night so you have
the whole next 12-hour period to pay him. Okay, and that's the
פסוק pasuk about do not let the sun set. Another פסוק pasuk
says לא תלין פעולת שכיר אתך עד בוקר, lo talin pe'ulat sachir
itcha ad boker, don't...
Don't let it sleep over, so that would be the case where
he worked in the day and you cannot, you have to pay
him during the following night, and if you don't pay him during
the following night, then it's still his money has slept over in
your possession, and in that case, you transgress לא תלין. lo talin.
Okay, so those are the two prohibitions, one for daytime and one
for night. So it says like this: שכיר יום גובה כל הלילה,
Sechir yom goveh kol halaila, a person that's a hired hand for
the daytime can collect the entire following night, meaning and otherwise you
will transgress if you don't pay him. The other הלכה halacha is
this point we've said earlier about being able to swear, you know,
if there's a dispute whether he's been paid or not, the worker
is believed during this immediate period afterwards. Okay, ושכיר לילה גובה כל
היום, Vesechir lailah goveh kol hayom, and somebody who worked at night,
his period of collecting is the whole following day. שכיר שעות גובה
כל הלילה וכל היום, Sechir sha'ot goveh kol halaila vechol hayom, if
somebody is working hourly, okay, he collects the whole night and the
day. Now, that's not exactly clear why that would be, we'll see
a whole debate in the גמרא, Gemara, but the basic lay for
now we'll say what that means is that he's worked into the
night or he worked some night hours. So therefore,
the time to pay him is the remainder of the night and
the whole following day. And why is that? It might be because
the night follows the day, so once you're already into the night
and you don't have the full night, you get the following day.
Or it could just be that the לא תלין פעולת שכיר lo
talin peulat sachir doesn't apply if it has not been a whole
night that you've withheld it. You've only haven't paid him for half
a night, so you wouldn't transgress לא תלין. lo talin. So the
only thing you would transgress is ולא תבא עליו השמש velo tavo
alav hashemesh at the end of the next day. Anyway, we'll see
more of that tomorrow. שכיר שבת, שכיר חודש, שכיר שנה, שכיר שבוע,
Sechir Shabbat, sechir chodesh, sechir shanah, sechir shavua,
so if they're hired for not just a few hours, they're hired
for a whole week or a month or a year or seven
years, יצא ביום גובה כל היום, יצא בלילה גובה כל הלילה וכל
היום, Yatza bayom goveh kol hayom, yatza balaila goveh kol halaila vechol
hayom, and this is a similar point. If he goes out in
the day like finally the seven years of work when יעקב Yaakov
finally finished working for לבן Lavan after seven years, if it was
noon, לבן Lavan had him pay him all up before sunset, ולא
תבא עליו השמש. velo tavo alav hashemesh. You know, that's the period
even if it was a huge long period that he's paying him
for. If he finished at 7:00 PM at night, he has until
6:00 PM sunset the next day. So again, you have this asymmetry,
and again, it's for one of two reasons: either because לא תלין
lo talin only applies if the whole night goes by, so in
a case where it's only part of the night, you don't transgress
with daybreak and you would only transgress with sunset. Or another explanation
is that, you know, once it's a partial thing, you will connect
it to the fuller unit if it's of the same day. So
if it's only a half a night, so oh, day, the day
follows the night, this is sort of what רש״י Rashi sounds like
in הלכה, halacha, so it's all halachically the same day. So since
you only got half a night, not a full night, we're going
to give you also the following day, the daytime. Whereas if you
only got half a day to pay him, well, the next night
is already halachically a different day, so sorry, you can't add that
on, you gotta pay him before sunset. Two ways of understanding it.
Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, תנו רבנן. Tanu
rabanan. מנין לשכיר יום שגובה כל הלילה? Mineyan lesechir yom shegoveh kol
halaila?
How do you know if he's a hired hand for the day,
he can collect all night? תלמוד לומר לא תלין פעולת שכיר אתך
עד בקר. Talmud lomar lo talin peulat sachir itcha ad boker. Do
not let it sleep over that night. And again, the assumption having
to be that you only are obligated once his period of work
is over. So that has to be somebody who worked for you
during the day, now when the night comes, you begin being obligated
and you can't hold it back the whole night. ומנין לשכיר לילה
שגובה כל היום? Umineyan lesechir lailah shegoveh kol hayom? How do you
know if he's worked at night that he has the whole day
to collect? שנאמר ביומו תתן שכרו, Shene'emar beyomo titein secharo, on that
day give him his payment. ואימא איפכא? Ve'eima ipecha? Maybe
when you're supposed to pay at night is when he worked at
night, when you're supposed to pay at day is when he worked
at day? No, שכירות אינה משתלמת אלא בסוף. Sechirut eina mishtalemet ela
basof. No, you're only obligated to pay for a hired hand, you
know, when the whole work is completed. So the employer's obligation
doesn't begin until the completion of the work. So he can't be
obligated to pay in a split second. So it has to be
that when you have the night to pay, it's when he worked
in the day, and when you have the day to pay, it's
when he worked in the night. All right, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
our rabbis taught: ממשמע שנאמר לא תלין פעולת שכיר אתך איני יודע
שעד בקר? Mimashma shene'emar lo talin peulat sachir itcha eini yode'a she'ad
boker? If it says "don't let it sleep over," so of course
it means until morning. We know that sleeping over ends by daybreak.
Why does it say עד בקר? ad boker? מה תלמוד לומר עד
בקר? Mah talmud lomar ad boker? מלמד שאינו עובר אלא עד בקר
ראשון בלבד. Melamed she'eino over ela ad boker rishon bilvad. To tell
you that only, you only transgress, this is fascinating, right? If you
didn't pay him, you transgress letting it sleep over. Do you continue
to transgress every next morning because you continue to let his wages
sleep over with you? So it says no, עד בקר ad boker
means there's only one morning that you transgress, which is pretty funny
because then it does not create much of an incentive. After he
already the employer blew it initially for him, now what? He's not
עובר over on anything else, so there's no loss to keep on
withholding the wages. So the גמרא Gemara says that. מכאן ואילך מאי?
Mikan ve'eilach mai?
So afterwards what is he transgressing? Because he's got to be transgressing
something, okay, otherwise he just won't have any incentive to pay. So
אמר רב, Amar Rav, said רב, Rav, עובר משום בל תשהא. over
mishum bal teshahe. He transgresses don't, you know,
delay the wages. You're not letting it sleep over but you're delaying.
That's very nice that there's no פסוק pasuk that says that. What
is that like a rabbinic איסור issur or something? So אמר רב
יוסף מאי קרא? amar Rav Yosef mai kra? Where do you get
this idea from a פסוק? pasuk? אל תאמר לרעך לך ושוב ומחר
אתן ויש אתך. Al tomar lere'acha lech veshuv umachar eten veyesh itach.
Do not tell your friend go and come back and yes I'll
get it later, I'll get it later and you have the money
on you, you know, so there's clearly a, which is exactly this
problem. So there's a פסוק pasuk in משלי Mishlei that says you're
not supposed to do that. So it's some type of a rabbinic
transgression, it does not seem like it's the דאורייתא d'oraita here at
all. A key word here is ויש אתך, veyesh itach, you have
the money. If you don't have the money on you, you're not
letting the wages sleep over in your possession. You don't have those
wages, you yourself have to collect the funds in order to pay
and that's a point that comes up later. Okay, we will end
here for today.